Clifford Berryman Cartoon Collection P008
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Clifford Berryman Cartoon Collection
1900-1948
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Berryman, Clifford Kennedy, 1869-1949
P008
5 Linear feet
Arrangement
Series 1: Community Issues, 21 cartoons (1900-1946) Cartoons in this series relate specifically to issues affecting residents of the District. Concerns include crowded schools, high rent, litter, noise, and pollution. A few cartoons address the growing population in D.C. Others deal with sports and recreation. Berryman also exercised his editorial role by drawing cartoons that served as public service announcements, such as ones encouraging participation in Community Chest campaigns, reminding citizens not to harm the dogwood trees, or calling for traffic safety and curfews. Series 2: Congressional Appropriations and District Finances, 10 cartoons (1929-1940) Cartoons here deal with a broad array of District financial issues, including Congressional appropriations, budget, spending, taxes, and a general lack of funds. Also included are cartoons reminding citizens of approaching tax deadlines. Many of these cartoons have overtones of Berryman's recurring theme of "taxation without representation" (see also Series 5: Representation). Series 3: Holidays and Events, 15 cartoons (1908-1942) The bulk of the cartoons here show scenes relating to holidays such as Christmas and Easter. Others address important days such as Inauguration and Teacher Appreciation Day, or prominent events in the city such as conferences and meetings. While there is one cartoon in this series relating to the Fourth of July, many more about this holiday as well as Flag Day can be found in Series 5: Representation, because Berryman often used these events as an opportunity to criticize the District's lack of representation. Series 4: Politics, 13 cartoons (1909-1938) Cartoons in this series discuss political figures, events, and controversies in a general manner. This collection does not contain many cartoons that comment on national politics. However, since D.C. is the seat of government, there was always plenty of political news in the city, so there are a number of drawings relating to the President and Congress generally. Most cartoons here deal with politics directly relating to the District government, such as ones commenting on the performance of the District commissioners, or the actions of Congressmen on the District committees. Series 5: Representation, 22 cartoons (1929-1947) These cartoons address the need for political representation for the District of Columbia. Berryman was a vocal proponent of full political rights for the District, and often lamented unfair conditions that required Washingtonians to pay taxes but denied them voting rights. The theme of "taxation without representation" appears frequently, often depicted as a ball-and-chain burden on his "D.C." character. Berryman often used occasions of national holidays to comment on lack of representation; see also: Series 3: Holidays and Events. Here, the Fourth of July, Flag Day, Election Day, and the anniversary of the Boston Tea Party were days when Berryman called for representation for the District. Cartoons also comment on the political developments and progress in the campaign to gain representation. Series 6: Weather and Nature, 16 cartoons, (1915-1917) These cartoons mainly comment on the weather in the District and the changing of the seasons. Berryman often laments the frigid winter, windy spring, and sweltering summer. One of his recurring characters here is a young girl depicting Spring, wearing a large hat covered in flowers. A few cartoons also relate problems of nature in the city, such as flies and starlings. Series 7: World War I, 7 cartoons (1917-1919) Cartoons here depict issues affecting District residents during the first World War, such as fundraising campaigns for government bonds, food shortages, and the return of war heroes. Series 8: World War II, 4 cartoons (1940-1945) This series contains a few cartoons specifically about World War II, which discuss the draft, war loans, and political conferences. Series 9: Artwork, 24 items (1934-1948) This series collects the handful of items in the collection that are not full-sized political cartoons from the Star. It contains Christmas cards, an invitation, a sketch, and printed caricatures, all drawn by Berryman.
Biographical / Historical
Clifford Kennedy Berryman was born in Versailles, Kentucky, on April 2, 1867 to James T. and Sallie C. Berryman, the tenth of eleven children. Berryman attended Professor Henry's School for Boys in Versailles and graduated in 1886. At the age of 13, Berryman drew a sketch of his idol, Representative (later Senator) C. S. Blackburn of Kentucky. Several years later, Blackburn saw the drawing displayed in Berryman's uncle's office, and was so impressed that in 1886 he sponsored the young man to come to Washington, D.C., procuring him a job as a draftsman at the United States Patent Office. Berryman added free hand drawings to illustrate and clarify the pictures accompanying applications for patents. From 1891 to 1896 he also worked as a general illustrator. During this time, he learned how to draw political cartoons by studying contemporary cartoons in Punch and Puck and copying the cartoonists' styles. Throughout his career, Berryman worked solely in the medium of pen and ink. On July 5, 1893, Berryman married Kate G. Durfee, a D.C. school teacher. The couple had three children, two of whom survived infancy. Later, son James followed in his footsteps, joining him as a staff cartoonist at the Star, while daughter Florence became the Star's art critic. Berryman sold his first series of drawings to the Washington Post in 1889 for $25, which was nearly his whole month's salary at the Patent Office. In 1896 he joined the Post staff full-time as a political cartoonist, acting as understudy to editorial cartoonist George Y. Coffin. Coffin died less than a year later, leaving Berryman to inherit the position. On February 1, 1907, Berryman moved to the Evening Star as chief cartoonist where he drew a cartoon every day until 1935, when he underwent a serious operation and subsequently reduced his workload from seven to three cartoons a week. Berryman won a Pulitzer Prize in 1944 for his August 28, 1943 cartoon entitled "But Where is the Boat Going?" which criticized unorganized manpower mobilization efforts during World War II. He also illustrated nearly forty books during his career, and was the first cartoonist to be accepted into the Gridiron Club. Berryman's most famous creation was the "Berryman Bear," the inspiration for the toy teddy bear. He first drew the bear in a Washington Post cartoon, inspired by an incident in which President Theodore Roosevelt refused to shoot a defenseless bear cub at the end of an otherwise fruitless bear hunt. Berryman depicted the event in a cartoon entitled "Drawing the Line in Mississippi" (November 21, 1902). Thereafter, whenever Berryman drew Roosevelt, the bear also appeared; after Roosevelt left office, the bear became the companion of Uncle Sam, representing the entire country. Berryman never commercialized his art and frequently gave away originals to anyone who wanted them. He collapsed on his way to work at the Star on November 17, 1949, and died less than a month later on December 11, 1949.
Custodial History
Clifford Berryman's daughter, Florence Berryman, most likely donated the cartoons sometime after his death, possibly in the early 1950s. However, the file on this collection does not document the details of this accession.
Related Materials
Washington Star Papers Collection, 061 Wichita State University, Clifford K. Berryman Collection of Political Cartoons, MS 88-01 George Washington University, Clifford Berryman political drawings collection, MS2286 The Historical Society of Washington, D.C., Clifford K. Berryman papers, 1835-1976, MS 0523 University of Georgia, Clifford K. Berryman cartoon, ms2420 Library of Congress, Clifford Kennedy Berryman papers, 1814-1965, MSS12559 Smithsonian Institute, Archives of American Art, Berryman family papers, 1829-1984, (bulk 1882-1961), OCLC number 1030335145 University of Wyoming American Heritage Center, James Thomas Berryman papers, 06563 National Archives, Berryman Political Cartoon Collection, 1896 - 1949, 306080
Scope and Contents
The Clifford Berryman Cartoon Collection contains 108 political cartoons drawn for publication in the Washington Evening Star from approximately 1900 to 1948. Drawn in pen and ink on posterboard, the majority of these oversized cartoons measure either 13.5" x 14.25" or 18" x 15.75". In general, the subjects of the cartoons pertain to local District of Columbia issues as opposed to national news. The cartoons address community issues, congressional appropriation and District finances, holidays and events, politics, District political representation, weather and nature, and World Wars I and II. The collection also contains a handful of miscellaneous Berryman drawings, cards, and caricatures. A brief description of each cartoon is provided with the box inventory at the end of the finding aid. Recurring characters in Berryman's cartoons include 1) "D.C.", a character resembling Benjamin Franklin who represents the people of the District of Columbia; 2) "Uncle Sam", representing the country as a whole; 3) "Berryman Bear",a small, fuzzy bear cub that was the inspiration for the toy teddy bear and appears with either President Theodore Roosevelt or Uncle Sam, usually to depict an emotional response to the situation occurring in the cartoon, or to stand for Berryman's own views on the matter; and 4) the Squash Center farmers, a group of men that provide various comments and opinions on news.
American newspapers; Political cartoons; Politics and government; Evening Star Newspaper Co.; Caricatures and cartoons
- Series 1: Community Issues, 1900-1946
  Scope and Contents
  Cartoons in this series relate specifically to issues affecting residents of the District. Concerns include crowded schools, high rent, litter, noise, and pollution. A few cartoons address the growing population in D.C. Others deal with sports and recreation. Berryman also exercised his editorial role by drawing cartoons that served as public service announcements, such as ones encouraging participation in Community Chest campaigns, reminding citizens not to harm the dogwood trees, or calling for traffic safety and curfews.
  - Original Number: 104, 1900-12-12; Caption: Something to be proud of Description: Uncle Sam doffs his hat to a female figure depicting Washington and holding the city shield and a bouquet of flowers [This cartoon, which appeared in the Washington Post, commemorates the 100th anniversary of the District as the nation's capital]. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Original Number: 97, 1909-07-08; Caption: none Description: An oversized man, gesturing at a clock that reads after midnight, begins to place a huge "Kimball Extinguisher" on top of a smaller figure who is playing a piano. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Original Number: 103, 1915-07-19; Caption: Making a Record Description: An oversized, proud "D.C." grins and holds the newspaper baseball page with the headline, "Nationals win 4 games in 2 days!" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original Number: 101, 1915-09-20; Caption: The Problem Description: "D.C." gazes at the pupils spilling out of the doors of District schoolhouses, labeled with various signs denoting overcrowding. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Original number: 76, 1925-06-10; Caption: All dressed up and nowhere to go! Description: "D.C." is at the water's edge dressed in his swimming outfit, but is upset to see a sign stating, "Tidal basin bathing beach closed by order of Congress." (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Original Number: 81, 1932-11-13; Caption: none Description: "D.C." gestures to figures representing the sick and the poor, and states the monetary amounts needed for the Community Chest in 1933. A sign reads explains that Washington faces the "greatest need for service to humanity" ever in the year ahead. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Original Number: 69, 1946-07-08; Caption: Washington Slept Here Description: A scene of a park full of litter, with newspapers and empty bottles all over the ground. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Original Number: 24, Caption: none Description: Surrounded by discouraging news stories, "D.C." reads that Walter Johnson promises the coming year will be his best ever. "D.C." exclaims, "Ah ha! All is not gloom!" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Original Number: 41, Caption: Another Glimpse of Beautiful Washington [in pencil] Description: A visitor is stuck in a traffic jam, surrounded by various wagons and trucks carrying trash and pollutants. The landscape is also covered by garbage. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Original Number: 45, Caption: none Description: A figure representing the Rent Commission sits on a fence before a raging bull labeled "Rent problems." A rhyme in the corner reads: "There once was a young man who said, 'How can I escape from this terrible cow? / I'll sit on this stile / And continue to smile / Which may soften the heart of this cow.'" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Original Number: 51, 1920; Caption: none Description: A man has just chopped off the entire top of a dogwood tree, and "D.C." says, "Think of the thousands you are robbing!" A sign in the background instructs, "Save the dogwood for others to enjoy." (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Original Number: 52, Caption: none Description: "D.C." tries to climb over a wall labeled "Full Community Chest Quota" to the clamoring masses on the other side, but Thoughtlessness, Carelessness, and Selfishness are holding him back. He says, "It's not a case of merely hoping! I've got to get over." (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Original Number: 54, Caption: none Description: "D.C." stands in the street in front of several small children playing baseball, and holds a traffic sign reading "Look Out: Children at Play!" (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Original Number: 55, Caption: none Description: A stern "D.C." grabs the arm of a young man who is pulling branches off a dogwood tree, and points to a sign reading "Don't Destroy the Dogwood." (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Original Number: 63, Caption: none Description: "D.C." surveys a hungry crowd from the Community Chest podium, and comments, "Greater needs than ever!" (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Original Number: 77, Caption: US Census Bureau says Washington will have 528000 population July 1 Description: A proud "D.C." looks in the mirror, noting a sign on the floor stating the District is "now estimated to be number thirteen in the select fourteen class," and says, "Number 13, eh? I should worry!" (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Original Number: 79, Caption: none Description: "D.C." pulls a Community Chest truck through the thick mud of Lack of Understanding and Lack of Sympathy, and says, "Lend a hand. It mustn't stop here!" (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Original Number: 88, 1916; Caption: The Day Description: Uncle Sam and the Berryman bear sprint out of an office, leaving a desk full of news stories and a sign on the chair stating, "Gone to the game." (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Original Number: 89, 1910; Caption: none Description: "D.C." leans against the White House gates next to a sign reading "Closed. No music here." He watches the festivities in the distance and mutters, "Too far away." (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Original Number: 94, 1908; Caption: Needed – A Curfew Law Description: At 10 p.m., "D.C." stands on a downtown street next to the movie theater, surrounded by lots of children playing without any supervision. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Original Number: 102, 1910; Caption: none Description: "D.C." surveys a river with a waterfall, holding an announcement of power plant plans and saying, "It's about time to put this water to work." (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series 2: Congressional Appropriations and District Finances, 1920-1940
  Cartoons here deal with a broad array of District financial issues, including Congressional appropriations, budget, spending, taxes, and a general lack of funds. Also included are cartoons reminding citizens of approaching tax deadlines. Many of these cartoons have overtones of Berryman's recurring theme of "taxation without representation" (see also Series 5: Representation).
  - Original Number: 78, 1929-03-10; Caption: none Description: "D.C." is caught up in interesting news stories, but Uncle Sam taps him on the shoulder and hands him a notice reading, "Don't overlook your income tax return--only 5 days left!" (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Original Number: 23, 1940-03-27; Caption: none Description: Surrounded by notices of financial problems facing the District, "D.C." yells into the phone, "I want to speak to Mrs. Roosevelt!" (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Original Number: 1, Caption: none Description: A District taxpayer uses a magnifying glass to peer at a wall listing the many individuals who are exempt from local income taxes. He comments, "I don't see my name on that list!" (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Original Number: 14, Caption: When a Feller needs a Friend! Description: A bedraggled "D.C." sits dejectedly on the curb while various politicians criticize and berate him. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Original Number: 16, Caption: none Description: Senator King says, "You're spending too much!" "D.C." is dressed in shrunken clothes and replies, "But it's you that're doing the spending for me!" (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Original Number: 21, Date: unknown Caption: The 400,000 city outgrows last year's suit [in pencil] Description: Uncle Sam reads about the commissioners' District budget estimate, as "D.C." stands before him in a shrunken suit holding notices about District financial needs. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Original Number: 57, Caption: What's this—the latest Strip-tease? Description: Oversized hands representing taxes have stripped "D.C." of most of his clothes and are tugging at his shirt. He yelps, "Leave me my shirt!" (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Original Number: 67, 1920; Caption: none Description: The Berryman bear is outside the District tax collector's office with a bullhorn warning the people pay their taxes on time and not get stung by penalties, as a sign states "One more day to pay taxes." (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Original Number: 70, Caption: none Description: Uncle Sam holds "D.C." upside down and shakes all the change out of his pockets while "D.C." yelps, "Brother can you spare a dime?" The Berryman bear covers his face in shame. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Original Number: 80, Caption: Sure Signs of Spring! Description: "D.C." is assailed by gale forces winds consisting of new taxes and a new appropriations bill. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series 3: Holidays and Events, 1908-1942
  The bulk of the cartoons here show scenes relating to holidays such as Christmas and Easter. Others address important days such as Inauguration and Teacher Appreciation Day, or prominent events in the city such as conferences and meetings. While there is one cartoon in this series relating to the Fourth of July, many more about this holiday as well as Flag Day can be found in Series 5: Representation, because Berryman often used these events as an opportunity to criticize the District's lack of representation.
  - Original Number: 107, 1908-12-24; Caption: Santa Claus Up to Date Description: Santa Claus has loaded all his presents onto a bi-wing plane, and chuckles, "This beats the old way." (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Original Number: 39, 1909-07-05; Caption: Safe and Sane Description: At a Fourth of July celebration with a program of events including "Fireworks on the White Lot," Uncle Sam asks "D.C.", "Isn't this better than going to the hospital?" (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Original Number: 64, 1934-12-05; Caption: none Description: "D.C." stands surrounded by mail packages and a sign reading "Shop Now, Mail Now." He reminds people to affix a "Season's Greeting 1934" stamp to their packages as well. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Original Number: 35, 1942-05-14; Caption: none Description: On Teacher's Day, Uncle Sam hands a busy teacher a bouquet of appreciation and says, "While you are handing out cards, Miss Schoolteacher, remember I've got one for you." (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Original Number: 36, 1915-1916; Caption: none Description: "D.C." thinks of the guardsmen stationed at the border and holds a sign promoting a "fund to provide a Christmas tree for the boys on the border." (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Original Number: 37, 1912; Caption: Day Before Easter Parade Description: "D.C." amusedly watches a line of shoppers struggle home under piles of brightly decorated packages. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Original Number: 44, 1916; Caption: Dreaming [in pencil] Description: A National Guardsman stationed on the border dreams of marching in a parade in D.C. on Inauguration Day. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Original Number: 46, Caption: none Description: "D.C." is dressed as a Scout leader, and waves flags welcoming the Boy Scouts to the city. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Original Number: 60, Caption: none Description: "D.C." holds a notice stating that Christmas stocks are ready early, and a postman instructs him to "Shop now! Mail now!" (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Original Number: 65, Caption: none Description: In front of the Warner Bros, NBC, and P.T.A. buildings, Uncle Sam and "D.C." shakes hands while "D.C." holds a notice about the Star's Christmas Drive, and a star overhead reminds readers to "Remember the forgotten child." (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Original Number: 74, Caption: none Description: "D.C." is decked out in all his holiday clothes and laughs, "First chance I've had to doll up since Santy came." (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Original Number: 85, 1914-1917; Caption: At the Busy Counter [in pencil] Description: A crowd of people carrying packages converge on a store gift exchange counter. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Original Number: 87, 1914-1917; Caption: Christmas Wishing [in pencil] Description: Two young government clerks look at the display window of the "U.S. Gift Shop," where Santa Claus is handing out salary increases, and say, "We may get in on that." (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Original Number: 105, 1915-12; Caption: none Description: An oversized "D.C." stands among a crowd of people, buildings, and signs announcing various conferences and meetings, and holds a list of congresses convening in Washington this week. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Original Number: 106, 1914-1917; Caption: none Description: Surrounded by notices encouraging citizens to get their holiday shopping done early, "D.C." imagines a crowd trying to squeeze into a subway car with all of their packages and decides he had better "hustle." (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Series 4: Politics, 1909-1938
  Cartoons in this series discuss political figures, events, and controversies in a general manner. This collection does not contain many cartoons that comment on national politics. However, since D.C. is the seat of government, there was always plenty of political news in the city, so there are a number of drawings relating to the President and Congress generally. Most cartoons here deal with politics directly relating to the District government, such as ones commenting on the performance of the District commissioners, or the actions of Congressmen on the District committees.
  - Original Number: 98, 1909-11-04; Caption: The Closed Season Description: Emmeline Pankhurst, a radical suffragette, arrives in Washington to campaign for votes for women, only to find the city deserted and all the buildings closed. "D.C." peers out from behind one of the buildings apprehensively. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Original Number: 95, 1912; Caption: none Description: Pinchot tried to give $600 to "D.C." but is refused. Teddy Roosevelt peers around the corner holding a campaign fund cup and says, "Hi there, Giff! I can use that!" (Box 4, Folder 2)